Guide to the Grace Reformed Church, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records, 1853-1964 AIS.1968.21
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Grace Reformed Church, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records
1853-1964
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Grace Reformed Church (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
AIS.1968.21
14.7 Linear Feet (28 boxes)
This collection contains the records of the Grace Reformed Church, Pittsburgh, PA, 1853-1964 and relates primarily to financial information and organizational infrastructure. These records include bank ledgers, statements, receipts, bills of sale, church programs, bulletins, missals, sermons, member lists, burial records, correspondence, meeting minutes, memoranda, and miscellaneous medias.
History
In December of 1853, Rev. Dr. Henry Harbaugh, president of Philadelphia based Franklin and Marshall College, was summoned to Pittsburgh at the request of resident Mrs. Amelia K. Schmertz concerning the potential establishment of a local organization of a Reformed Church. The result of this visit contributed to the 1854 establishment of the Pittsburgh congregation of the Grace Reformed Church, a denomination of The Reformed Church in the United States (RCUS). Services were first held in a hall at the corner of Smithfield Street and Virgin Alley in downtown Pittsburgh and included an initial congregation of seven charter members. A year later the Grace Reformed Church purchased three vacant lots on the corner of Grant and Webster Streets and prepared plans for the construction of a new building. Completed in December of 1857, the original church structure of the Grace Reformed Church would serve the needs of its congregation for just under six years.
In 1899, confronted with an increasing number of members leaving downtown for the suburbs, the Church purchased a plot of land in the Oakland neighborhood of Pittsburgh situated at the corner of Dithridge and Bayard Streets and in October 1901 began construction on a new edifice. Completed two years later in July 1903, this new structure served as the permanent location of the Grace Reformed Church until 1964, when the congregation was forced to dissolve due to shrinking numbers in membership and increasing financial instability. In 1968 the Church was demolished.
The RCUS was founded in 1725 as a German immigrant denomination. In 1934 a vast majority of Reformed Churches, including the Grace Reformed Church, united with the Evangelical Synod of North America to form the Evangelical and Reformed Church. In 1957 this new church merged with the Congregational Christian Churches to form the United Church of Christ. Although officially uniting with the Evangelical Synod of North America in 1934, there still exists roughly forty RCUS denominations in the United States today. The majority of these are located in the Northern Plains, South Central, and Western parts of the United States.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection reflects the proceedings and daily affairs of the Grace Reformed Church, Pittsburgh, PA as represented through various correspondence, financial records, and organizational materials, 1853-1964.
The collection is comprised of five series. Series I consists of material related to the history of the church, 1853-1954. Series II contains information regarding organizations affiliated with and sponsored by the church, 1903-1964. Series III consists of material related to church affairs and proceedings. Included in this series is the correspondence of the Rev. Dr. John H. Prugh, pastor of Grace Reformed Church from 1880-1915, and the correspondence of Louis A. Meyran, a considerable benefactor and member of the church consistory. This series also contains church member and roster lists in addition to miscellaneous burial records and dates 1903-1964. Series IV consists of material related to church finances 1855-1964. Included are numerous bank statements and ledgers as well as bills, receipts, and correspondence from local Pittsburgh businesses. Series V contains ten glass lantern slides, assorted photographs, and several stamps used to mark church documents and official correspondence. The small collection of lantern slides feature landscapes and monuments of biblical significance and were most likely utilized as teaching aids for bible class and Sunday school lessons.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Grace Reformed Church, Pittsburgh, Pa., 1968.
Previous Citation
Grace Reformed Church Records, Pittsburgh, Pa., 1853-1964, AIS.1968.21, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
Official records of Grace Reformed Church, such as membership, baptisms, marriages and deaths are designated as RG 384 and located at the Evangelical and Reformed Historical Society, Lancaster Theological Seminary, 555 W. James Street, Lancaster, PA 17603.
Oakland (Pittsburgh, Pa.) -- Religion; Church records; Marriage records; Church buildings -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; German Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Religion; Churches and Synagogues; Ethnic groups; Death records; Golden Triangle (Pittsburgh, Pa.) -- Religion; German Reformed Church (U.S.); Grace Reformed Church (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Reformed Church in the United States
- History, 1853-1954; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series I contains programs, bulletins, newspaper clippings, notes, and publications pertaining to the history and governing rules of the Grace Reformed Church. Also included is the 1853 journal of the Reverend Dr. Henry Harbaugh describing his visit from Philadelphia to Pittsburgh and detailing the potential appropriateness of Pittsburgh as a setting for the Grace Reformed Church.
  - Journal of Reverend Dr. Henry Harbaugh, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Church Bulletin, Historical Sketch of Grace Church, 1854-1902 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Church Bulletin, Golden Jubilee Celebration, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Church Bulletin, Centennial Anniversary Celebration, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Handwritten History of Grace Church, no date (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Church History, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Program of Dedication, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Constitution and Bylaws, no date (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Member Duties and Visitor Rules, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Grace Reformed Church Annual Pew Prices and Interior Blueprint, no date (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Scrapbook, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings, 1903-1915 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Organizations, 1903-1964; II.
  Series II contains record books, attendance books, registers, annual reports, bulletins and announcements, meeting minutes, and correspondence related to those organizations and classes affiliated with and sponsored by Grace Reformed Church. Records of the various women's guilds and other groups are found within this series.
  - Sunday School, 1895-1959; 1.
    - Record Book, 1903-1956 (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
    - Pupil Workbook and Teacher Guide, 1952, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Accounts Receivable Ledger, 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Attendance Book, 1916-1936 (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
    - Attendance Book, 1952-1959 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Primary Department, Attendance Book, 1904-1927 (Box 3, Folder 3-5)
    - Library Register, 1895-1902 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Board Meeting Minutes, 1953-1956 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Men's Bible Class, 1911-1921; 2.
    - Meeting Minutes, 1911-1921 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1912 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Member and Attendance Book, 1914-1917 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Women's Bible Class, 1914-1936; 3.
    - Meeting Minutes, 1914-1936 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Annual Report, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Annual Report and Roster, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Women's Guild, 1942-1960; 4.
    - Women's Guild, Annual Reports, 1942, 1956-1960 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Pittsburgh Synodical Women's Guild, Eighth Biennial Meeting, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Women's Guild of the Evangelical and Reformed Church, Annual Reports, 1956-1958 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Women's Missionary Society, 1896-1928; 5.
    - Roster and Meeting Minutes, 1925-1928 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Receipts and Disbursements, 1896-1920 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1910-1912 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Young People's Society, 1911-1917; 6.
    - Ledger, Roster and Meeting Minutes, 1911-1917 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Consistory, 1904-1964; 7.
    - Meeting Minutes, 1904-1949 (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
    - Correspondence, 1908-1928, 1931-1950 (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
    - Member and Committee Lists, 1914-1953 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Announcements and Bulletins, 1950-1964 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Survey, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Council of the Reformed Churches of America, 1912; 8.
    - Committee Report of Foreign Missions, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence and Minutes, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - United Church of Women, 1963; 9.
    - Annual Report, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Pittsburgh Synod of the Reformed Church, 1916-1959; 10.
    - Bulletins and Minutes, 1916-1952 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous and Correspondence, 1940-1959 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Affairs and Proceedings, 1903-1964; III.
  Series III contains service bulletins, sermons, church missals, correspondence, memoranda, member lists, burial records, and pledge and communicant cards related to internal affairs and general church proceedings. Also included are miscellaneous service bulletins, pamphlets, publications, and announcements of non-affiliated Grace Reformed churches.
  - Rev. Dr. John H. Prugh, Correspondence, 1911-1912 (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
  - Louis A. Meyran, Correspondence, 1924-1941 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Memoranda and Notes, 1911-1912 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1903-1956 (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
  - Miscellaneous Cards of Appreciation, no date (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Invitations, no date (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Sermons, 1920s (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
  - Service Bulletins, 1914-1955 (Box 8, Folder 1-21)
  - Service Bulletins, 1956-1964 (Box 9, Folder 1-9)
  - Miscellaneous Service Bulletins, Non-Grace Reformed Church, no date (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Pamphlets and Publications, Non-Grace Reformed Church, no date (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Men of Grace Reformed Church Roster List, 1911 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Committee and Church Member List, 1912 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Church Member List, 1938 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Church Member Lists, no date (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Church Guestbook, 1952-1955 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Member Transfer Requests, 1952-1960 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Cradle Roll Call Certificate, 1927 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Burial Records, 1927-1946 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Church Pledge Cards, 1921-1931 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Advent Pledge Cards, no date (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Cards for Communicants, no date (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Pamphlets and Publications, no date (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Finances, 1855-1964; IV.
  Series IV contains bank bonds, deposit slips, check books, bank statements, ledgers, leases, and deeds related to the financial history of the Grace Reformed Church. The bulk of the content relates to church financial records and includes correspondence, monetary transactions, and bills of sale and receipts from local Pittsburgh businesses. Also included are the last wills and testaments of Louis A. Meyran and Paul H. Hacke.
  - Financial Bond, 1855 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Mortgage Indenture, 1855-1856 (Box 11, Folder 2-3)
  - Financial Bond, 1872 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Financial Indenture, 1872 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Financial Bond, 1880 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Financial Contract, 1900 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Bill of Property Sale, 1901 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Financial Records, 1903-1911 (Box 11, Folder 9-17)
  - Pew Rent Pledges, 1911 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Financial Records, 1912-1937 (Box 12, Folder 1-25)
  - Financial Records, 1938-1947 (Box 13, Folder 1-11)
  - Financial Records, 1948-1955 (Box 14, Folder 1-10)
  - Financial Records, 1956-1964 (Box 15, Folder 1-6)
  - Grace Reformed Re-decorating Fund, Financial Records, 1956 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Financial Records, no date (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Last Will and Estate Information, Paul H. Hacke, 1938 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Last Will and Estate Information, Louis A. Meyran, 1941 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Deposit Slips, Germania Savings Bank, 1912 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Checks Paid, Germania Savings Bank, 1912-1916 (Box 16, Folder 2-3)
  - Deposit Slips, The Colonial Trust Company, 1940-1956 (Box 16, Folder 4-6)
  - Workingmans Savings Bank and Trust Co., Bank Statements, 1942 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Peoples First National Bank and Trust Co., Bank Statements, 1953-1957 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - The Fidelity Trust Company, 1954-1956 (Box 17, Folder 1-4)
  - The Fidelity Trust Company, 1956-1957 (Box 18, Folder 1-3)
  - The Colonial Trust Company, 1938-1939 (Box 18, Folder 4-5)
  - The Colonial Trust Company, 1939-1943 (Box 19, Folder 1-7)
  - The Colonial Trust Company, 1943-1946 (Box 20, Folder 1-7)
  - The Colonial Trust Company, 1947-1950 (Box 21, Folder 1-7)
  - The Colonial Trust Company, 1950-1952 (Box 22, Folder 1-5)
  - the Colonial Trust Company, 1953-1954 (Box 23, Folder 1-4)
  - Unknown Bank Ledger Books, 1908-1911 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Ledgers, The Colonial Trust Company Bank, 1928-1956 (Box 24, Folder 2-5)
  - Ledgers, Workingmans Savings Bank and Trust Company, 1942 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Deposit Slips, Peoples First National Bank and Trust Company, 1953-1956 (Box 24, Folder 7)
- Media Material, V.
  Series V contains lantern slides, stamps engraved with the bust of the Rev. Dr. John H. Prugh, and assorted photographs. The small collection of lantern slides were purchased from the T.H. McAllister Company, NY, NY and most likely utilized as teaching aids for Sunday and Bible school classes. Unless specified, all dates unknown.
  - Lantern Slides, 1.
    - Solomon's Walls, Jerusalem (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Second Pyramid, Giza, Egypt (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Ruins of Fortress Tyre, Lebanon (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - View of Mount of Olives from Damascus Hotel (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Unknown (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Jupiter's Temple, Baalbek, Lebanon (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - Convent of Mar-Saba, Jerusalem (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - Nablus (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Ramallah (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - Unknown (Box 25, Folder 10)
  - Engraving and Stamp, 2.
    - Wood Stamp Copper Block Engraving, Bust of Rev. Dr. John H. Prugh (Box 25, Folder 11)
    - Rubber Stamp, "My Testimony For Christ" (Box 25, Folder 12)
  - Photographs, 3.
    - Rev. Karl Stein and Family (Box 26, Folder 1-3)
    - Church Treasurer Frank Freese and Family (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Consistory (Box 26, Folder 5-6)
    - Unidentified Churches (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Photographic Negatives, 4.
    - Photograph Negatives, Rev. Karl Stein (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Photographs, Miscellaneous, 5.
    - Photographs, Miscellaneous Unknown (Box 27, Folder 1-6)
    - Photographs, Miscellaneous Unknown (Box 28, Folder 1-14)